hello and welcome to computer architecture for everybody let me start with a question
why should a software developer or honestly anyone learn about hardware because today computers can
feel like magic you open a laptop you run a program and somehow everything just works but before we
decide that computer technology is magic i want to take you on a journey imagine that we're looking
at that laptop together we start zooming in past the keyboard past the case past the circuit boards
until we're staring at a chinese chip but we don't stop there then we zoom in even further
into the wiring into logic pathways and finally a single transistor that's what this course is
about it's not about becoming a hardware engineer not memorizing electrical equations but gaining a
little more x-ray vision into the machines that we use every day this course is for a few different
kinds of learners maybe you're young and just starting to learn programming and you want deeper
intuition about what your code is really doing maybe you went to college years ago and took a
hardware class that felt weird or abstract or too difficult or intimidating and you never quite
felt like you understood it think of this course as a nice second chance to actually understand
what you were taught back then maybe you're a computer science student worried about an
upcoming architecture class this course will not replace that class but it will make it feel
familiar approachable and give you a rough outline of the concepts you're going to learn
or maybe you're just a long time practicing software engineer someone who already builds
real systems but it would help you to understand a little bit more about what's going on under the
hood now a quick word about ai if you like using ai tools this course is actually a great place to
use them many of the ideas we explore nand gates logic circuits machine instructions are all things
that ai understands really well so if something feels confusing and my lecture doesn't go into
enough detail ask ai to explain it in a different way ask for diagrams ask for examples as a matter
of fact much of the software autograders that you're going to be using was built with the help of ai
so in this class ai is not cheating it's a study partner a collaborator another view another lens
that helps you see deeper the exercises in this course are meant to feel more like video games
than traditional assignments you'll experiment you'll explore you'll gently design pieces of
hardware logic without the pressure of actually becoming a professional chip designer my goal is
simple by the end of this course i don't expect you to be a hardware expert but i do hope that
when you look at a computer you will imagine the layers inside machine language cpus circuits
transistors and maybe you'll smile just a little because computers won't feel so much like magic
anymore welcome to computer architecture for everybody let's start peeling back the layers