so now i want to talk to you about how manufacturing transistors evolved go from sort of the earliest
manufactured transistors to sort of the modern day and how we manufacture transistors so the key thing
that has made the difference is transistors started with a certain size and the goal was to make them
smaller and smaller and package them in different ways over time so originally there were individual
transistors connected on a circuit board to other transistors and resistors etc then after a while
we would buy these things called integrated circuits ICs little black things with the legs on them
and they would have some gates inside of them you know maybe a couple of AND gates or a couple of
NOT gates or a NOR gate or something and the little we could connect up and make use of these gates
by connecting to the little legs and then we'd have traces on the underlying medium to make sure
that we connected the right signals to the right gates much like we've been doing
now at some point things changed so prior to 1960s the transistors were assembled
sort of i'll show you in a sec kind of like lego blocks and they were three-dimensional objects you
would manufacture different materials and then you would kind of put those materials together like
lego blocks in 1960 fairchild introduced the 2N1613 transistor and this was manufactured by a
two-dimensional process meaning that there was a substrate underneath of it and then they did
stuff on that substrate with manufacturing and out came a transistor instead of like assembling
transistors they would like lay down transistors almost like painting transistors versus building
transistors and this led eventually to very large-scale integration where you could in a
three millimeter by four millimeter chunk put 2,300 transistors plus associated resistors etc
and so that's what led to the the intel 4004 and which was the first commercially available single
chip microprocessor the thing that eventually made this all possible was a thing called
photolithography i mentioned that planar transistors are in effect manufactured almost like
with a paint roller on it but they weren't exactly a paint roller they had these masks
so the paint didn't roll on everywhere so their paint rolled on where there were no
where there were no lines and so we would produce these VLSI layouts and then we would make in a
sense transparencies with clear areas and then dark areas and then we would project light through
and then with lenses make it small and then plate and then project this onto a substrate and then
expose that substrate to various chemicals with various processes and the net result was flat
transistors okay and that that really made it a lot easier than sort of assembling tiny little
precise pieces and that led us to ultimately VLSI design so let me show you a few artifacts and
explain them to you so let's start here this is the Fairchild 2N1613 let's see if you can see it
it looks kind of like a spacecraft it also looks like war of the worlds they used to come through
and scare us so that is an actual transistor from 1960 which was the first widely available
planar transistor before that i've shown you things like so this sony radio that i showed you
earlier this has bjt transistors now they don't look all that different on the outside but inside
they are constructed very differently and so let me grab these legos here and show you how the
bjt's were constructed you would get various materials right and then you would you would
basically have to kind of construct them together and make like a sandwich and then you would
contact wires to make this little sandwich and you would connect a wire to the middle part the
top part and the bottom part and that's how you would make a bjt transistor okay so it's like a
lego block it's like a stack with different materials that are in a sense combined together
to make a transistor now what they did instead and i don't really have anything to show you though
to the planar transistor started with a flat substrate okay and so the flat substrate would
look somewhat like this this is a piece of silicon and then what they would do is they would sort of
paint the lines on it and then they would expose it through photolithography and then they would
put get circuits and then we'll cut them up and then you'll put each little one inside one of
these transistors again the manufacturing is not lego like it's more painting like spray painting
with masking okay and then that what that did was that led to making the chips or the transistor
smaller and smaller and smaller and more vlsi design again that you're going to play with in
this course this is a 1986 rockwell silicon wafer and on this you can see there's just about 120
chips they're about a quarter inch on each side let's zoom in as much as we can
so
these transistors are very small but this is 100 chips and then what they would do is they would
come through and they would cut along these lines and they would solder little tiny wires at the edge
of each of these chips and then they would put the chips inside of the package with the little legs
so i'm mixing my technologies here but here is a intel 404 and inside this little tiny package
come on little tiny package so you can see this little tiny package and you can see the little
legs on the tiny package so there were tiny little wires it's all very small the little
chip is inside here and then the wires would go from the outside and be soldered onto the chip
and then the chip would be covered and that's kind of what this looks like so i can show you a much
more modern chip and so you can kind of see it so that the piece that gets cut out of the silicon
wafer on this amd processor is here and then all these wires and pins eventually find their way
to the inputs and outputs of the actual chip but these trans each one of these little quarter
inch chips now that was a 2008 processor but this is a 1986 processor so that is an example of how
photolithography can build a lot of chips quickly with a two-dimensional process sort of painting
with masks painting with chemicals and masks that create these chips that we then cut out and put
into little tiny packages or medium-sized packages so that we can install them into motherboards
into computers and connect them up to the outside world with all of these technologies transistor
count went crazy so if you think about 1971 the intel 4004 had 2300 transistors the first billion
transistor chip was the intel itanium and there's some of these deep learning are are basically
wafer style integration so you build a wafer like this and you have these wafers not just connected
these this wafer was designed to be cut into pieces but imagine building a chip that's the size
of a wafer a deep learning wafer scale engine by service has 2.6 trillion transistors in 2020
the two terabyte flash memory with 5.3 trillion gates and the blackwell b1000 b100 cpu with 208
billion transistors in 2024 so we've got a lot and we're starting to create things that make use
of the entire wafer there's a lot of complexity and a lot of reliability because a lot of these
chips turn out wrong in the wafer scale and so up next you're going to learn about vlsi
design and how you draw the pictures that become the patterns that create the gates and the traces
in a chip on one of these silicon wafers