so we just got done adding numbers with gates with carry but now we're going to do something a little
more difficult which is storing data with gates and so that basically is a way we can create memory
systems whether it's registers inside of the cpu or high speed memory we can create ways to store
zeros and ones over time the key there is over time so it'll take us a while to develop this concept
but the key thing here is that we use feedback loops and in this circuit which calls is called
a set reset latch it basically has this q output and the q not output and you'll notice that the
there's a top NOR gate and a bottom NOR gate and the top output is get put as one of the inputs
to the bottom NOR gate and the bottom output is put as one of the inputs to the top NOR gate
now you'll look at the little srq truth table and and what happens is if q has a value
and s and r are zero the value of q will be maintained so let's just let's just trace that
through so let's just assume that r and s are zero and q is one so the the one from q is the
second input to the lower NOR gate and that is a one input so the output of this lower NOR gate
is a zero which is then the input to the top NOR gate and as soon as the the the input the
the q not input to the top NOR gate is zero and r is zero as well then that means that q is one
because it's a NOR gate and q is one so it goes to the bottom but q q being one and s being zero
means that q not is zero the zero goes back up r being zero and a zero zero zero equals one
so what happens is once q is one it stays one it's sticky now you can put in combinations
of s and r to set the value for q if you look at the truth table if you set s to zero and r to one
then the q becomes a zero and then if you set the r back to zero it's q stays zero and if you set
s to one and r to zero then q becomes a one but then if you set that s back to zero then q maintains
so we can store either a zero in the q or a one in q and then as long as we keep the inputs
s and r zero that one just goes round and round and round between those two NOR gates
so we're going to cover this a little bit more here's the truth table now we're just not going
to show those NOR gates we're just going to call this an sr latch again that's what we do we make
take two gates and make a component so we can talk about it when s and r are zero the latch
maintains its internal state that q output of one says that means that we set it to one at some
previous time and now we're just putting inputs of zero zero and the output stays one so if we have
s of one and r of zero then that makes the internal storage to one and then what you've got to do
is you've got to take that s down to zero but then the output maintains so two zeros means
keep your state now if we make the s be a zero and the r be a one that's going to set the output
to zero and then the next thing you do is you set r to zero and then the output stays now how we
do this is a little bit tricky right and we'll we'll make smarter latches but this is the simplest
latch and it's literally two NOR gates okay that's it now we're gonna have to build some more logic
because this is kind of inconvenient because that 2-1 situation is kind of a pain in the neck now
i'll just let you know that you can try to build an sr latch using two NOR gates in my simulator
and it won't work now maybe someday i will make the circuit emulation of my digital logic simulator
better but the problem is is that because this is a time-based circuit with feedback you have to build
a circuit emulation that understands that these two things are happening round and round and round
and round and you can build them but it's a lot harder to build them because you have to deal with
time rather than just zeros and ones flowing through a circuit so my circuit emulator because
i want to keep it simple and easy to use it really deals with what we call combinatoric circuits which
kind of the ones and the zeros move from one side to the other but the feedback ones i can't do it
so what you have to do in my circuit emulator is use the sr component which does work because it's
not really two NOR gates it's a little component that the software understands so don't yell at me
and don't file a github issue if you try to build an sr latch and it doesn't work and that's under
under unfortunate okay so i mentioned that the sr latch is kind of clunky right the sr latch is
you're you're not allowed to give it one one as input okay and so the latch that is more useful
is what we call a gated d latch and the gated d latch has basically a clock input and a data input
and the way it works is as long as the clock is zero q stays the same thing right so whatever
it was before and as soon as clock is set to one that then copies d into the internal state so if
you set clock to one and d to zero the internal state becomes zero and if you set clock equals one
and d equals one then the internal state is one and then you set clock back to zero and that zero
or one stays over time if you look at it there's several ways to build it but in this case i'm
using two NAND gates with the feedback loop and then you're kind of there's like an s and an r in
the middle of it but then there's this the d and the c are set up so that it can never send the wrong
value into the the sr like latch right so you have this bit of logic in the beginning that says
when c is one copy d into the latch part and when c is zero ignore what is happening on d
so that's another way to look at this if we start with one in the state in the internal value
and we have the clock of zero and the d is zero that at this point d is being ignored because the
clock is zero then what we want to do is we want to store a zero in it so we we pulse the clock to
be one and that at that moment copies the zero into the one bit latch and then we can set the
clock back to zero and then the zero will be remembered so we don't really care what the d
value is once the clock is back to zero you can flip the d value back as much as you like when the
clock is zero so you can set d to one the clock is still zero and the output is still zero then you
pulse the clock by setting it to one and then the one is copied into it and to the output and then
when we're done copying we set the clock back to zero and the d is one but then you can set the d
to zero because as the while the clock is zero the d is being ignored and so you can see how the
you put whatever value you want on the d and then you pulse the clock to copy d into the latch
that's why they called it a gated d latch the clock acts as the gate when the clock is high
it copies its input when the clock is low it ignores its input and we're going to do what we
always do and that is combine these things 3d latches and we're going to make a three
bit register and we're going to represent in this three bit register numbers from zero through seven
so we have three bits a ones bit a twos bit and a fours bit and we're going to have a switch that
has ones twos and fours that's going into the d of each of the corresponding ones and then we
have a single clock pulse we're going to pulse them all at the same time so the internal storage
of the bits is one zero one and so we can take the output of the three bits and feed it into a nixie
tube and get it out once we can build this we don't need to make three one bit latches we can
make a three bit latch and that's what we're going to use going forward and that's pretty much what a
register is inside of a microprocessor in that it's a three bit latch and somewhere it's getting its
operands a ones column a twos column and a fours column and then we pulse the clock to copy from
those inputs into the register so the register then the clock goes back to zero so the register
stores a value for a while until we hit the clock button and it copies its inputs again then we take
the clock back to zero and then it stays the same after a while we'll we'll use the convenience
stuff now we have registers and we have nixie tubes and we can copy the output of the register
to the nixie tube and we can see what the value is inside of the nixie tube and so you can see
that we're slowly but surely you know building all the stuff that might eventually become a
microprocessor right you know we're building logic putting them together i don't know what this might
be this might be a half adder for all i know from an old 1970s computer but slowly but surely we
are deciding what to put on our cpu traces which is wires and gates transistors to do addition
subtraction jumping the kinds of things that computers want to do