so now that you've learned to program a microprocessor from the 1970s i'd like to take a quick fast forward from the 1970s to the present
lots changed since the 6502 was available as a $25 microprocessor
since the 1970s there have been about 50 distinct CPU families
i've been part of this my whole career lots of research and innovation
adoption, switching, computer vendors picking one CPU and then switching to another CPU
generational turnover and overall approach from complex instruction sets to simpler
risk instruction sets from large refrigerator size mainframes to micro small microprocessors
then larger microprocessors faster microprocessors interestingly after all that things have settled
down in the modern era there are two major CPU families in use if you think about consumer
and server and desktop if you take computers and phones and bring them together about 90 percent
of the marketplace is ARM based processors and the remaining 10 percent is Intel processors
ARM is very successful because it was focused on low power and as computers have gotten faster and
faster we really care more and more about saving power both for small handheld devices and for
desktops and then even laptops and so power savings is really important and the ARM was
designed to save power so let's take a quick case study and look at Apple over the over the years
Apple the Apple I was one of the early adopters of the 6502 in 1997 and the in the Apple II and
the Apple II and its sort of whole family were a very successful set of microprocessors for a long
time Apple switched to a different processor the Motorola 68000 from 1984 to 1994 but during that
time they were playing with a project called the Newton which was a handheld device wasn't
extremely popular but it was a handheld device battery powered handheld sort of pocket that was
using an ARM processor an ARM processor then I then they switched from the Motorola to the Power
PC in 1994 and again 12 more years they used the Power PC and then the Intel x86 in 2006 they
switched their Macintosh line from using Power PC to Intel x86 I was actually in the audience when
Steve Jobs announced the switch from Power PC to Intel x86 I was I was amazed I was sitting I was
working on my laptop which had a Power PC in it I've been using it for years and at the end he
threw the doors open and we ran into some rooms and there were some prototype Intel x86 Macintosh
is running Mac OS and it was amazing to me that they could switch from Power PC to Intel x86 then
the iPhone came out in 2007 and I was also in the audience when Steve Jobs announced the first iPhone
this iPhone 1 and I was carrying around at that point in time I was carrying around a trio as my
main computer and the trio was one of the things he put up on the screen when he was talking about
the iPhone but the iPhone had an ARM a Samsung ARM in it and so this is an ARM processor
and then in 2020 the ARM came not just to the iPhone but from the Macintosh ARM is not
manufactured by one organization the ARM is licensed to many folks to build them and Apple
builds its own hardware in the Macintosh from 2020 to present and what's interesting about that
is Apple is currently redesigning their CPUs continuously every year they have a new release
they call it the m1 the m2 the m2 max m2 3 pro or whatever and what they're doing is they're
actually studying what needs to be in their microprocessor and they add instructions to their
to their ARM systems based on what they think we need we use these for whether it's image
processing or audio or video gaming or now increasingly artificial intelligence and one
of Apple's advantages is because they use the ARM and they license the core instruction so the ARM
but then they add their own instructions and then manufacture them another thing about Apple that's
kind of interesting is you've been using an emulator a code that's written in JavaScript
that makes it look like you can run 6502 processors well in 2005 as Apple was moving from PowerPC to
Intel processors they included a technology called Rosetta 1 and then when they were moving from
Intel to ARM processors in 2020 they included a technology they called Rosetta 2 and of course
that's a reference to the Rosetta stone a famous stone with the connected multiple languages from
sort of antiquity to latin-based languages and so what Rosetta did in both cases it translated the
machine code from a previous computer to the modern one and the the interesting thing was is
it would often run because the modern processors they were they were choosing whether it be the
Intel initially or ARM later they were so fast that they could emulate the previous generation
processors almost at the same speed as the hardware of the previous generation and so this really made
it a lot easier for those of us who were Apple customers making a transition from architectures
which otherwise would have almost been impossible to go from from a major one major CPU architecture
to another architecture so fun aside there is sort of this indirect connection between the 6502
and the ARM and ARM stands for Acorn Risk Microprocessor and it was built in Cambridge England by Acorn
and if you Acorn originally built a thing called the BBC Micro which was a 6502 based microcomputer
more popular in the UK and so they decided they were going to create a new microprocessor so they
knew a lot about 6502 the goal was not to make a better 6502 but there was a lot of homage to
the 6502 in the ARM and so they used BBC Micro's to build and simulate the ARM design ARM1 had
25,000 transistors the 6502 had 4,500 transistors and the ARM1 through whatever there's many
generations of arms and they are the most widely used processors in the world and for a good time
you can ask AI to make this historical leap connection between the 6502 ARM and the Raspberry
Pi and I have a picture of Sophie Wilson one of the architecture designers of the initial ARM
working at Acorn working on both the BBC Micro and the building of the ARM microprocessor.