so welcome to our lecture where we start talking about the speed, clock speed, how circuits have delay
in the previous lecture we introduced for the first time the notion of a clock and that is
a value that is at zero and then when we want something to happen we set it to one and when we're done we set it back to zero
now this is a circuit, it's a combinatoric circuit
and if you play with this online you'll see that it, you change a number and it takes a little bit of time for the
propagation to end up at the output of this circuit
and that's just because it's kinda slow in my online emulator
this is a full adder circuit and
this is not a very long circuit but you can see over time how these are going to get longer especially
when we start chaining them
right so if we make a four bit adder that's
four full adders where the carry out goes to the carry in
the carry out of the second one goes to the carry in of the third and the carry out of the third one goes to the fourth
now
those values will only settle down after the carries have propagated all the way down that chain and that's just a four bit adder
you could have a thirty two bit adder or a sixty four bit adder
or even a multiplier in hardware and so the
propagation through a sixty four bit
multiplier
is going to take a little while
and so these circuits get more complex than what we've done
but when they build them they'll make a sixty four bit adder
it takes two operands and produces a result
and the designers of the chip hardware will
simulate and simulate and tweak it and simulate and simulate it
how long
is it that if you present inputs to a sixty four bit adder
until the outputs are reliable
and no longer changing
and that's called the clock rate
and if we take a
microprocessor
we compute the delay of the slowest element or longest path
in the arithmetic and logic unit
we can determine the number of times per second we can reliably do computations
and then we set the clock rate
to be a little conservative
and so this is another example of the Intel 4004 which is our favorite little first
widely available commercial microprocessor
and so as
microprocessors have gotten smaller as the width of each wire and with the
transistors have gotten smaller you can make the distances between the
transistors smaller
as we went to CMOS and we could manage heat better
we could put things more tightly packed the more tightly packed we do
the faster they go and so
this is a graph of a thing called Moore's law and it was
something that
people just started seeing once we would improve the technology then we would
build microprocessors with
that new technology then we improved the architecture of those microprocessors
and then we would do new technology
it turned out that
the number of integrated circuits and pretty much for a while
the clock speed of them would double about every
every two years
so how do we know what the clock rate is like I mentioned
the size of the chip because when we're doing things this fast the speed of light
matters
the number of transistors because each transistor takes a little while
to flip as you change its input and its output needs to change
the physical length
of any long path and just because a chip is
one inch wide doesn't mean there's not paths that are several inches because
they go round and go back and forth
and the speed at which transistors switch and this depends on the technology
and it gets better over time
and like I said these chips are laid out and simulated endlessly
during development to figure out how we can take this chip
and then you've probably heard about people overclocking their chips
and that's when someone changes the clock
because they think that the factory was being too conservative on the clock
rate so let's
add 10% and see if it starts blowing up and that's called overclocking
so let's play with a simple circuit we're going to take
two of the circuits that we built in previous lectures
and combine them together so what we're going to do is we're going to take an
adder and a clock and a register
so the adder simply takes two three-bit numbers from zero through seven
on the A ones, twos, and fours for the A and ones, twos, and fours for the B
and so we have our two operands we have our
sum values which are the sum and they are copied to the input values
of our latch and we have a clock on the latch because if you recall
while the clock is low we don't care about the input changes
okay so right now our adder is zero
we're adding zero plus zero and getting zero our latch
is still a zero not because the adder is zero but because the clock is zero and the latch
was zero before
if we change the input on the adder we're going to do a
two plus four, A is two, B is four
and the adder now has produced it there's a delay there
but you'll notice the latch hasn't changed because we haven't pressed the
clock yet the clock is still at zero
and the definition of the clock in a latch is that the latch is ignoring its
input change
any changes on input until the clock
goes one so when the clock goes one the sum values are latched
into the latch memory now if you keep the clock one and fiddle with the inputs
of the adder
then you're not sure what's happening because it may take a while to go through
the adder or might come through
very quickly but the smart thing to do is then
set the clock back to zero because we have the sum copied
from the adder and now we can change the inputs
right once we have the clock at zero we can just
feed different inputs into the adder so now we're adding
four plus three now the clock is still zero
and we have changed the inputs to the adder we're now adding
four plus three what the adder is reflecting the sum
as soon as we change those inputs right the adder just as a
combinatoric circuit takes its inputs produces the output
but because the clock is still zero the clock is low
the latch hasn't accepted those values yet right when the clock goes high
the seven is going to be copied into the new
latch value now if we do this you can build this circuit with my
little circuit emulator you can build a circuit where you have
the adder you have a latch and you can interactively play with the
ones twos and fours for both the a input and the b input
but instead of having a button for the clock we have a programmable clock
and the clock object goes from zero to one
back to zero every second so what happens is
you can fiddle with the inputs of this see how fast you can change them
and every second whatever is in the adder is going to be copied
into the latch now we're going to go a little farther in the next lecture
with what we're doing with clocks and gates and adders and latches